<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2011-12-20T21:54:06-08:00</published>

	<id>bd656794-f3c5-4f78-8642-bcabece31c88</id>

	<title>Discovery Of General Intelligence</title>

	<category term="Intelligence" />
	<category term="Psychology" />
	<category term="Psychometrics" />

	<content type="xhtml">
		<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<div class="quote">
				<blockquote>
					<p>
						Intelligence tests were originally created with the practical goal of identifying students in need of alternative education (Binet &amp; Simon, 1916).
						Because intelligence tests were originally devised to predict school grades, the items were intentionally designed to measure a general ability to profit from explicit instruction, concentrate on task, and engage in intellectual material.
						Indeed, research shows that such a general ability does seem to exist.
						Over a century ago, Spearman (1904) discovered that when a wide range of cognitive tests that have explicit instructions and require effortful concentration is administered to a diverse group of people, all of the tests tend to be positively correlated with one another, a finding often referred to as a "positive manifold."
						Spearman labeled the factor on which all individual tests loaded <i>g</i>, for general intelligence.
					</p>
					<p>
						Over the past 100 years, the existence of <i>g</i> as a statistical phenomenon is one of the most replicable findings in all of psychology (Carroll, 1993; Chabris, 2007; Jensen, 1998).
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						<b>Binet, A.</b>, &amp; <b>Simon, T.</b>
						(1916)
						<i>The development of intelligence in children</i>
						(E. S. Kite, Trans.).
						Baltimore, MD: Williams &amp; Wilkens.
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						<b>Spearman, C.</b>
						(1904).
						"General intelligence," objectively determined and measured.
						<i>American Journal of Psychology</i>,
						<b>15</b>, 201-293.
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						<b>Carroll, J. B.</b>
						(1993).
						<i>Human cognitive abilities: A survey of factor-analytic studies.</i>
						Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						<b>Chabris, C. F.</b>
						(2007).
						Cognitive and neurobiological mechanisms of the Law of General Intelligence.
						In <b>M. J. Roberts</b> (Ed.),
						<i>Integrating the mind: Domain general vs. domain specific processes in higher cognition</i>
						(pp. 449-491).
						New York, NY: Psychology Press.
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						<b>Jensen, A. R.</b>
						(1998).
						<i>The g factor: The science of mental ability.</i>
						Westport, CT: Praeger.
					</p>
				</blockquote>
				<p class="quote-by">
					-- <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.scottbarrykaufman.com/">Scott Barry Kaufman</a>
				</p>
				<p class="quote-from">
					from "The Cambridge Handbook of Intelligence"
				</p>
			</div> <!-- class="quote" -->
		</div>
	</content>
</entry>
