<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-06-16T20:03:26-07:00</published>

	<id>42a7aa7e-536a-41d4-9420-b7c126f82a33</id>

	<title>Who Tends To Be The Smartest (By Career): Engineers, Mathematicians, Computer Scientists And Physical Scientists</title>

	<category term="Intelligence" />
	<category term="Psychology" />
	<category term="Psychometrics" />

	<content type="xhtml">
		<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<div class="quote">
				<blockquote cite="http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/finding-the-next-einstein/201108/how-brainy-is-your-major">
					<p>
						First, an important disclaimer: the data I'm about to present to you is based on <i>averages</i>.
						A group average does not imply that everyone who is a part of that group is at the average.
						Therefore, <b><i>this data should not be used to indicate that someone who majored in subject A is necessarily smarter than someone who majored in subject B</i></b>, because that is a comparison of two individuals.
						To adequately make that comparison, we would need their individual scores.
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						The following [...] [rank order] is based on <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.projecttalent.org/">Project TALENT</a>, a stratified random sample of the nation's high school population (a sample of over 400,000).
						In <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.vanderbilt.edu/Peabody/SMPY/Wai2009SpatialAbility.pdf">some of my research</a> along with my colleagues <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.vanderbilt.edu/Peabody/SMPY/david_lubinski.htm">David Lubinski</a> and <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.vanderbilt.edu/Peabody/SMPY/camilla_benbow.htm">Camilla Benbow</a> of Vanderbilt University, we examined the group of individuals from this sample who had earned a higher educational degree (a bachelor's, master's, or Ph.D.).
						We looked at measures of verbal, spatial, and math ability [...]
					</p>
					<p>
						<b>
						Here is the rank order of the groups examined:
						<br />
						1. Engineering
						<br />
						2. Physical Science
						<br />
						3. Math/Computer Science
						<br />
						4. Biological Science
						<br />
						5. Humanities
						<br />
						6. Social Science
						<br />
						7. Arts
						<br />
						8. Business
						<br />
						9. Education
						</b>
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						So, are these results replicated in other samples?
						The answer is yes.
						We also <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.vanderbilt.edu/Peabody/SMPY/Wai2009SpatialAbility.pdf">examined data from the Graduate Record Examination</a> (GRE).
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						[T]he fact that we see the same pattern in a select sample (GRE) in addition to a nationally representative stratified random sample (Project TALENT) illustrates that the average score patterns for majors are quite robust.
					</p>
					<p>
						When taking the GRE, individuals are asked to indicate which major they intend to pursue for graduate study.
						[...]
						The [...] [rank order] below takes an average of the math and verbal subscores to indicate general ability.
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						<b>
						Here is the rank order of the groups examined:
						<br />
						1. Engineering
						<br />
						2. Math/Computer Science
						<br />
						3. Physical Science
						<br />
						4. Biological Science
						<br />
						5. Humanities
						<br />
						6. Arts
						<br />
						7. Social Science
						<br />
						8. Business
						<br />
						9. Education
						</b>
					</p>
				</blockquote>
				<p class="quote-by">
					-- <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.tip.duke.edu/node/960">Jonathan Wai</a>
				</p>
				<p class="quote-from">
					from "<a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/finding-the-next-einstein/201108/how-brainy-is-your-major">How Brainy Is Your Major?</a>"
				</p>
			</div> <!-- class="quote" -->
		</div>
	</content>
</entry>
