<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-03-18T17:58:46-07:00</published>

	<id>7e2456ab-c45c-44b6-8840-1982a83ae7ce</id>

	<title>Curiousity, Conscientiousness And Intelligence Important or Academic Performance</title>

	<category term="Intelligence" />
	<category term="Psychology" />
	<category term="Psychometrics" />

	<content type="xhtml">
		<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<div class="quote">
				<blockquote cite="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2011/10/111027150211.htm">
					<p>
						Curiosity [...] [is] good for the student.
						That's the conclusion of a new study published in <i>Perspectives in Psychological Science</i>, a journal of the Association for Psychological Science.
						The authors show that curiosity is a big part of academic performance.
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						Intelligence is important to academic performance, but it's not the whole story.
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						One of those is conscientiousness [...].
						People who score high on this personality trait tend to do well in school.
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						von Stumm and her coauthors wondered if curiosity might be another important factor.
						"Curiosity is basically a hunger for exploration," von Stumm says.
						"If you're intellectually curious, you'll go home, you'll read the books.
						If you're perceptually curious, you might go traveling to foreign countries and try different foods."
						Both of these, she thought, could help you do better in school.
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
						They found that curiosity did, indeed, influence academic performance.
						In fact, it had [...] about the same [effect] as conscientiousness.
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						S. von Stumm, B. Hell, T. Chamorro-Premuzic.
						<b>The Hungry Mind: Intellectual Curiosity Is the Third Pillar of Academic Performance.</b>
						<i>Perspectives on Psychological Science</i>,
						2011; 6 (6): 574 DOI: <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/1745691611421204">10.1177/1745691611421204</a>
					</p>
				</blockquote>
				<p class="quote-from">
					from "<a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2011/10/111027150211.htm">Curiosity Is Critical to Academic Performance</a>"
				</p>
			</div> <!-- class="quote" -->
		</div>
	</content>
</entry>
