<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-10-29T00:23:22-07:00</published>

	<id>1a533520-0773-4abd-9c1c-d65f09ccd0af</id>

	<title>Sphingolipids and Axonal Growth</title>

	<category term="Neuroscience" />

	<content type="xhtml">
		<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<div class="quote">
				<blockquote cite="https://www.weizmann.ac.il/Biological_Chemistry/scientist/Futerman/Buccoliero02.pdf">
					<figure style="text-align:center;padding-top:2em;">
						<a
							href="http://changelog.ca/quote/2012/10/29/sphingolipids_and_axonal_growth/sphingolipids_and_axonal_growth.png"
						><img
							src="http://changelog.ca/quote/2012/10/29/sphingolipids_and_axonal_growth/sphingolipids_and_axonal_growth.png"
							style="width:80%;"
						/></a>

						<figcaption>
							<p>
							[...]
							Inhibition of sphingolipid synthesis and degradation have opposite effects on neuronal development.
							Inhibition of sphingolipid synthesis by fumonisin B1 or D-PDMP results in a decrease in the rate of axonal growth and a reduction in the number of axonal branch points.
							In contrast, accumulation of GlcCer by incubation with conduritol-B-epoxide stimulates axonal growth.
							The figure show camera lucid drawings of representative neurons on day 3 in culture, after addition of the inhibitors on day 0.
							See text and references (17–19,38,39) for more details.
							The bar in the box of the control neuron corresponds to 100 ␮m, and examples are given for the control neuron showing the various morphological features of hippocampal neurons.
							3-ketoSa, 3-ketosphinganine; Sa, sphinganine; Dihydro-Cer, dihydroceramide; Cer, ceramide; GlcCer, glucosylceramide; GSLs, glycosphingolipids.
							</p>
						</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						17.
						Futerman, A. H.,
						Boldin, S.,
						Brann, A. B.,
						Schwarz, A.,
						and
						Zisling, R.
						1998.
						Regulatory roles for sphingolipids in the growth of polarized neurons.
						Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 845:176–187.
					</p>
					<p>
						18.
						Futerman, A. H.
						1998.
						Distinct roles for sphingolipids and glycosphingolipids at different stages of neuronal development.
						Acta Biochim. Pol. 45:469–478.
					</p>
					<p>
						19.
						Futerman, A. H.,
						Boldin, S. A.,
						Brann, A. B.,
						Pelled, D.,
						Meivar-Levy, I.,
						and
						Zisling, R.
						1999.
						Regulation of sphingolipid and glycosphingolipid metabolism during neuronal growth and development.
					Biochem. Soc. Trans. 27:432–437.
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						38.
						Schwarz, A.,
						Rapaport, E.,
						Hirschberg, K.,
						and
						Futerman, A. H.
						1995.
						A regulatory role for sphingolipids in neuronal growth.
						Inhibition of sphingolipid synthesis and degradation have opposite effects on axonal branching.
						J. Biol. Chem. 270:10990–10998.
					</p>
					<p>
						39.
						Schwarz, A.
						and
						Futerman, A. H.
						1997.
						Distinct roles for ceramide and glucosylceramide at different stages of neuronal growth.
						J. Neurosci. 17:2929–2938.
					</p>
				</blockquote>
				<p class="quote-by">
					-- Rosaria Buccoliero
					 , Jacques Bodennec
					 , <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.weizmann.ac.il/Biological_Chemistry/scientist/futerman/">Anthony H. Futerman</a>
				</p>
				<p class="quote-from">
					from "<a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.weizmann.ac.il/Biological_Chemistry/scientist/Futerman/Buccoliero02.pdf">The Role of Sphingolipids in Neuronal Development: Lessons from Models of Sphingolipid Storage Diseases</a>"
				</p>
			</div> <!-- class="quote" -->
		</div>
	</content>
</entry>
