<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-09-22T21:46:18-07:00</published>

	<id>b6836a6d-6493-4ad6-971b-4bd3addc248c</id>

	<title>Asperger As Predictor Of Programming Aptitude?</title>

	<category term="Asperger" />
	<category term="Autism" />
	<category term="Computer Science" />
	<category term="Psychology" />
	<category term="Psychometrics" />

	<content type="xhtml">
		<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<div class="quote">
				<blockquote cite="http://www.ppig.org/papers/19th-Wray.pdf">
					<p>
						[M]ight it be possible that measurements of mild autistic-spectrum tendencies would show a useful correlation with programming ability? The popular image of an expert programmer is a man (seldom a woman) careless of physical appearance, socially inept, with narrow and intense interests and a peculiarly literal way of interpreting spoken or written statements.
						While this is a stereotype, there is some truth in it, and all of these characteristics are commonly shared by people with a mild autistic-spectrum condition or Asperger syndrome.
						This is not fanciful association, since it has been observed that scientists and engineers are more likely to have autistic-spectrum conditions than the general population and that fathers and grandfathers of autistic-spectrum children are more likely to work as scientists and engineers (6).
					</p>
					<p>
						Only a self-administered test would be practical.
						However, rather than use a direct measure of autistic tendencies such as AQ (7), it was decided to use a pair of instruments, “Systemizing Quotient” (SQ) and “Empathy Quotient” (EQ).
						These are designed to be used together and the quantity SQ – EQ has been shown to have a strong correlation with independent diagnoses of Asperger syndrome and other autistic-spectrum tendencies (8).
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						An experiment was therefore designed to test the hypothesis that SQ and EQ scores, either together or individually, would be strongly correlated with a measure of programming ability. 
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						The SQ and EQ tests both have values in the range 0 to 80, with fairly similar distributions.
						They were designed to be used in conjunction and the value SQ – EQ has been shown to be significantly different for males, females and Asperger syndrome individuals (8).
						Plotting SQ – EQ against programming test score, in figure 8, we see a high correlation (r = 0.67, p = 0.002).
					</p>

					<br />
					<figure style="text-align:center;">
						<a href="http://changelog.ca/quote/2012/09/22/aspie_programmer/sq-eq_versus_programming_test_score.png"><img
							src="http://changelog.ca/quote/2012/09/22/aspie_programmer/sq-eq_versus_programming_test_score.png"
							style="width:80%;"
						/></a>
						<figcaption>
							<b>Fig. 8.</b> SQ – EQ plotted against programming test score.
						</figcaption>
					</figure>

					<p>
						For this class, mean programming test score was 6.8 (SD = 2.4), median 8; the mean SQ was 34.3 (SD = 12.0), median 33; the mean EQ was 34.5 (SD = 11.7), median 33; the mean SQ – EQ was -0.2 (SD = 15.9), median -1.
						In contrast, for the general population of males the mean SQ is 30.3 (SD = 11.5) and the mean EQ is 41.8 (SD = 11.2) (10, 11)
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						6.
						BBC:
						<i>Scientific brain linked to autism.</i>
						BBC, London.
						Available from: <a rel="nofollow" href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/4661402.stm">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/health/4661402.stm</a>
						(2006)
					</p>
					<p>
						7.
						S. Baron-Cohen, et al.:
						<i>The Autism Spectrum Quotient (AQ): Evidence from Asperger Syndrome/High Functioning Autism, Males and Females, Scientists and Mathematicians.</i>
						Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders 31:5-17
						(2001)
					</p>
					<p>
						8.
						Goldenfeld, N. et al.:
						<i>Empathizing and Systemizing in Males, Females and Autism.</i>
						International Journal of Clinical Neuropsychiatry 2, 338-345
						(2005).
					</p>
					<p>
						[...]
					</p>
					<p>
						10.
						Baron-Cohen, S., et al:
						<i>The Systemising Quotient (SQ) : An investigation of adults with Asperger Syndrome or High Functioning Autism and normal sex differences.</i>
						Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society, Series B, Special issue on "Autism : Mind and Brain" 358:361-374
						(2003)
					</p>
					<p>
						11.
						Baron-Cohen, S.
						and
						S. Wheelwright:
						<i>The Empathy Quotient (EQ). An investigation of adults with Asperger Syndrome or High Functioning Autism, and normal sex differences.</i>
						Journal of Autism and Developmental Disorders 34:163-175
						(2004)
					</p>
					<p>
						
					</p>
				</blockquote>
				<p class="quote-by">
					-- <a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.stuartwray.net/">Stuart Wray</a>
				</p>
				<p class="quote-from">
					from "<a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.ppig.org/papers/19th-Wray.pdf">SQ Minus EQ can Predict Programming Aptitude</a>"
				</p>
			</div> <!-- class="quote" -->
		</div>
	</content>
</entry>
