<?xml version="1.0"?>

<entry xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<published>2012-10-28T10:16:55-07:00</published>

	<id>8c021bc8-3598-481b-8f87-655193029e70</id>

	<title>An Evolutionary Theory On Why Men Love Breasts</title>

	<category term="Evolution" />
	<category term="Psychology" />

	<content type="xhtml">
		<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
			<div class="quote">
				<blockquote cite="http://www.livescience.com/23500-why-men-love-breasts.html">
					<p>
						Larry Young, a professor of psychiatry at Emory University who studies the neurological basis of complex social behaviors, thinks human evolution has harnessed an ancient neural circuit that originally evolved to strengthen the mother-infant bond during breast-feeding, and now uses this brain circuitry to strengthen the bond between couples as well.
						The result?
						Men, like babies, love breasts.
					</p>
					<p>
						When a woman's nipples are stimulated during breast-feeding, the neurochemical oxytocin, otherwise known as the "love drug," floods her brain, helping to focus her attention and affection on her baby.
						But research over the past few years has shown that in humans, this circuitry isn't reserved for exclusive use by infants. 
					</p>
					<p>
						Recent studies have found that nipple stimulation enhances sexual arousal in the great majority of women, and it activates the same brain areas as vaginal and clitoral stimulation.
						When a sexual partner touches, massages or nibbles a woman's breasts, Young said, this triggers the release of oxytocin in the woman's brain, just like what happens when a baby nurses.
						But in this context, the oxytocin focuses the woman's attention on her sexual partner, strengthening her desire to bond with this person.
					</p>
					<p>
						In other words, men can make themselves more desirable by stimulating a woman's breasts during foreplay and sex.
						Evolution has, in a sense, made men want to do this.
					</p>
				</blockquote>
				<p class="quote-by">
					-- <a rel="nofollow" href="https://twitter.com/nattyover">Natalie Wolchover</a>
				</p>
				<p class="quote-from">
					from "<a rel="nofollow" href="http://www.livescience.com/23500-why-men-love-breasts.html">New Theory on Why Men Love Breasts</a>"
				</p>
			</div> <!-- class="quote" -->
		</div>
	</content>
</entry>
